A Finding Aid to the Howard Wise Gallery Records, 1943-1989, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Howard Wise Gallery records
1943-1989
Archives of American Art
Howard Wise Gallery
AAA.howawisg
Archival Resource Key
11.4 Linear feet
The records of the Howard Wise Gallery in New York, and its predecessor the Howard Wise Gallery of Present Day Painting and Sculpture in Cleveland, Ohio, measure 11.4 linear feet and date from 1943-1989. Records consist of correspondence, artist files, exhibition files, business records, writings, and video recordings that document the activities of Wise's gallery in Cleveland from 1957-1961 and, to a lesser extent, his gallery in New York City from 1960-1970. Wise's activities following the closing of the Howard Wise Gallery are also found among the correspondence, artist files, business records, writings, and video recordings.
Historical Note
After twenty-five years as president of Arco Company, his family's industrial paint and varnish manufacturing business in Cleveland, Howard Wise (1903-1989) sold his interest in the business and began to pursue his own artistic interests. The Howard Wise Gallery of Present Day Painting and Sculpture opened in Cleveland in 1957 and operated for the next five years. It first showed School of Paris and New York painters and also sold prints. With the exception of a few collectors and loyal customers, Clevelanders did not appreciate Wise's efforts to bring the best new art from all over the world to the city. The Cleveland Plain Dealer ran several editorials ridiculing modern art in general and Howard Wise and his gallery in particular. Attendance was poor and Wise decided to relocate to New York.
After a year of searching for a suitable location and renovating the space, Howard Wise Gallery opened at 50 West 57th Street in 1960. The gallery generated excitement among visitors and artists, and sales and attendance were much better than in Cleveland. After closing the Cleveland gallery in 1961 Wise never again returned to his native city. Despite being well received and conducting significantly more business in New York, the gallery was not a great financial success. Between 1962 and 1965, art consultant Douglas MacAgy, a friend and the former director of the Dallas Museum of Art, worked with Wise in running the gallery. Although the critics were not always favorably impressed, Howard Wise Gallery had a significant following and made important contributions through its support of the use of technology in art, specifically kinetic and light sculpture and the video art movement.
By the late 1960s, Wise recognized that a gallery setting was not suitable for many of the new art forms. He closed Howard Wise Gallery in 1970 so that he could focus his energy and resources on exploring the best way to support environmental sculpture, political work, and video art. Wise founded Electronic Arts Intermix in 1971. Originally an artist-run umbrella organization, today Electronic Arts Intermix is a non-profit videotape distribution service and editing facility, that has amassed an important and highly regarded video art collection.
Existence and Location of Copies
Many of the video recordings have been preserved, and digital copies are available for researchers in the Archives of American Art offices.
Material lent for microfilming is available on 35mm microfilm reel N70-77 at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Howard Wise Gallery in New York, and its predecessor the Howard Wise Gallery of Present Day Painting and Sculpture in Cleveland, Ohio, measure 11.4 linear feet and date from 1943-1989. Records consist of correspondence, artist files, exhibition files, business records, writings, and video recordings that document the activities of Wise's gallery in Cleveland from 1957-1961 and, to a lesser extent, his gallery in New York City from 1960-1970. Wise's activities following the closing of the Howard Wise Gallery are also found among the correspondence, artist files, business records, writings, and video recordings.
Correspondence documents the operations of Wise's galleries in Cleveland and New York. A few subject files and a small amount of Howard Wise's personal correspondence (some pre-dating and post-dating the galleries) are also included in this series.
Artist files contain varying combinations of correspondence, printed material, notes and writings, and photographs. Most artists represented in this series were affiliated with Howard Wise Gallery either in Cleveland or New York City, but some files are for individuals of potential interest to the gallery, and those of continued interest to Wise after the closing of the gallery. Exhibition files contain correspondence, printed material, guest lists, and notes. Exhibition files are not a comprehensive record of exhibitions held in Wise's galleries.
Business records include records of cash disbursements that are primarily for Howard Wise's travel and entertainment expenses. Business memoranda and correspondence between the Cleveland and New York galleries document sales, inventory, shipments and financial information. Also among the business records are photographs of the Howard Wise Gallery of Present Day Painting and Sculpture in Cleveland, a set of slides of artworks and installation views dating to the late 1950s, and inventories and loan documentation related to Howard Wise's personal art collection. Writings consist of essays and speeches by Howard Wise, writings on Howard Wise and the Howard Wise Gallery artists by Douglas MacAgy and Marita Sturken, and a typescript recollection of a dinner party conversation with Supreme Court Justice Warren Burger from 1973.
Video recordings include 41 videoreels and videocassettes, a log book of video shot by Wise in the early 1970s, and a program for a screening of his videos held in Wellfleet, Mass. Recordings are mainly unedited footage of interviews with artists and community figures, gallery openings, and other community events in Wellfleet, Mass. and the greater Cape Cod region. A log book and detailed labels on videos provide details about their content. Three edited works made by Wise from the raw footage include "video portraits" of Serge Chermayeff, Edwin Dickinson, and Jack Tworkov. Also found is footage from the premiere performance of Jean Dubuffet's Coucou Bazaar at the Guggenheim Museum, and a dinner party attended by Dubuffet. Video of works by other artists include footage from media and kinetic artworks shown in the Howard Wise Gallery from 1964-1967, as well as a video performance by Hannah Wilke from 1974.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 5 series:
Missing Title
Series 1: Correspondence, 1943-1984 (Boxes 1-2; 2.0 linear ft.)
Series 2: Artist Files, 1950-1984 (Boxes 3-6; 3.4 linear ft.)
Series 3: Exhibition Files, 1957-1968 (Boxes 6-7; 0.9 linear ft.)
Series 4: Business Records, 1957-1989 (Boxes 7-9; 2.6 linear ft.)
Series 5: Writings, 1957-1984 (Box 9; 4 folders)
Series 6: Video Recordings, 1973-1985 (2.5 linear feet)
Provenance
In 1979, the Howard Wise Gallery lent material to the Archives of American Art for microfilming. The rest of the collection was donated by Howard Wise in 1971 and by Barbara Wise, Howard Wise's widow via Dana Kasarsky, Wise's daughter-in-law in 2011.
Separated Material
The Archives of American Art also holds microfilm of material lent for microfilming (reel N70-77) including publicity materials, correspondence, exhibition plans, text of an exhibition catalog, and photographs relating to Howard Kiesler. Lent materials were returned to the lender and are not described in the collection container inventory.
Related Material
Also found in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Howard Wise conducted by Paul Cummings on February 22, 1971. The Harvard Art Museum Archives also holds archival records of the Howard Wise Gallery.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Video art; Art, Modern; Photographs; Interviews; Video recordings; Kinetic sculpture; Art galleries, Commercial -- New York (State); Art galleries, Commercial -- Ohio; MacAgy, Douglas, 1913-; Tworkov, Jack; Wise, Howard; Burger, Warren E., 1907-1995; Sturken, Marita, 1957-; Dubuffet, Jean, 1901-; Dickinson, Edwin Walter, 1891-1978; Chermayeff, Serge, 1900-
- Correspondence, 1943-1984; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 2 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence with collectors, clients, art dealers, museums, arts organizations, and suppliers of goods and services documents the Howard Wise Gallery of Present Day Painting and Sculpture, Cleveland, Ohio, and the Howard Wise Gallery, New York, New York. A few subject files and a small amount of Howard Wise's personal correspondence (some predating the gallery and some dated after the gallery closed) are interfiled with the alphabetical correspondence in 1.1: Correspondence, A-Z. Among these are photocopies and a transcribed typescript of a letter from Wise's father, Samuel D. Wise, conveying property to the Camp Wise Association in 1907.
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged as 2 subseries in alphabetical and chronological order respectively. Files within the alphabetical correspondence contain multiple correspondents grouped together, with selected correspondents listed in the container listing. Additional correspondence related to gallery business is found in Artist Files, Exhibition Files, and Business Records.
  1.1: Correspondence, A-Z, 1943-1967
  1.2: New York Gallery Correspondence, 1962-1965
  - Correspondence, A-Z, 1943-1967; 1.1; Archival Resource Key
    - Abrams, H. N., Incorporated - American District Telegraph Co., 1958-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Abrams, H. N., Incorporated
      Abrams, Morris
      Academy of Medicine of Cleveland
      Adath Jeshurun
      Addison Gallery of American Art
      Addressograph-Multigraph Corporation
      Adler, Arthur M., Jr.
      Agris Verlag Krefeld und Baden-Baden
      Akron Beacon-Journal
      Allan Stone Gallery (see: Stone Gallery, Allan)
      Albert R. Lee and Co., Inc. (see: Lee, and Co., Inc., Albert R.)
      Alevy and Cantor
      Alexander Iolas Gallery (see: Iolas Gallery, Alexander)
      Allen Inc., Publishers, Howard
      Alpers, Dr. N.
      Amel Gallery
      American Academy in Rome
      American District Telegraph Co.
    - American Federation of Arts, 1956-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - American Honda - Art Colony, 1957-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
      American Honda
      American Iron and Steel Institute
      American Mutual Liability Insurance Company
      American Republic Insurance Company
      A. M. Sachs Gallery (see: Sachs Gallery, A. M.)
      Anderson Gallery, David
      Andrews Moving and Storage Co.
      Angle, Gertrude N.
      Ansbacher, Carolyn
      Architects Collaborative
      Architectural Forum
      Arco Company
      Art Colony
    - Art Dealers Association, Inc., 1961-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    - Art Gallery of Toronto - Ayers, Kirby, 1957-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Art Gallery of Toronto
      Arthur Tooth and Sons, Ltd. (see: Tooth and Sons, Ltd., Arthur)
      Art Information Service ( see also: Chamberlain, Betty)
      Art Institute of Zanesville, Ohio
      Artist Tenants Association
      Artistes de France Associates Incorporated
      Artists Equity Association
      Arts Club of Chicago
      Art:USA:NOW
      Ashbrook, J. B.
      Aujourd'hui
      Austin, Allan
      A. W. Fenton Co., Inc. (see: Fenton Co., Inc., A. W.)
      Ayer and Son, Inc., A. W.
      Ayers, Kirby
    - Babcock Gallery - B'nai Brith Hillel Foundation of Western Reserve University, 1980; 1957-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Babcock Gallery
      Baekland, Brooks
      Baille, Bruce
      Baker, Oliver and Sylvia
      Baker, Richard Brown
      Balaban, M.
      Balkwill, S. Ward
      Ball State Teachers College
      Barker, Walter
      Barnard College Club of Cleveland
      Barnes, Marion J.
      Barone Gallery
      Barton, Bruce, Jr.
      Bates, Mary Louise
      Baum School of the Allentown Art Museum
      Baycrafters
      Bayer, Eleanor
      Baylor University
      Beaird, Jane R.
      Bedi-Rassy Art Foundry
      Bell, J.
      Beneson, Charles B.
      Bennett, Richard M.
      Berger, Frank
      Bergmann, Robert
      Bertha Schaefer Gallery (see: Schaefer Gallery, Bertha)
      Bescherner, H.
      Bey, Edie
      Bianchini Gallery
      Biddle, Mary A.
      Biehle, Helen C.
      Bill, Max
      Bing, Louis S.
      Birmingham Festival of Arts
      Bishop, Robert H.
      Blesh, Rudi
      B. L. Marble Chair Company (see: Marble Chair Company, B. L.)
      B'nai Brith Hillel Foundation of Western Reserve University
    - Bode, Arnold - Butler Institute of American Art, 1956-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Bode, Arnold
      Bolles Gallery
      Bollinger Transport
      Bolton, Frances P.
      Bolton, Kenyon C.
      Bond, Douglas
      Bonfoey Company
      Boone, Pat
      Borgenicht Gallery, Inc., Grace
      Borsick, Helen
      Bosse, M. J.
      Boston Truck Company
      Bourlet and Sons, Ltd., James
      Boutourllilne, Serge
      Bovasso, Julie
      Bowker Company, R. R.
      Bragazzi, Olive
      Brahan, Diane W.
      Brantford Arts Council
      Brata Frame Shop
      Brazilian Consulate General
      Breeze, Marion
      Brighten, Jonny
      Broadway Maintenance Corp.
      Broder, Harry
      Bronfman, Anne
      Brooklyn Heights Art Show and Sale and Auction ( see: Charity Exhibitions)
      Brooklyn Museum
      Brooks, David
      Brophy, William E.
      Brown, Leonard
      Brown University
      Brownheim, Mary and L. M.
      Bruce, Alice
      Buchanan, Harvey
      Buckwalter, Charles
      Budworth and Son, Inc., W. S.
      Bulger, E.
      Bundy Art Gallery (see: Carpenter, Harlow)
      Burden, William A. M.
      Burkhardt, Rudy
      Burnham, J. S.
      Bury, Pol
      Butler Institute of American Art
    - Cage, John - Carmel Gallery, Hilda, 1957-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Cage, John
      Cain, Edward R.
      Calray Sales and Service Inc.
      Cambridge Camera Exchange
      Camp Wildwood (see also: Wildwood, Camp)
      Canton Art Institute
      Cardona, Rudi and Electra
      Carmel Gallery, Hilda
    - Carpenter, Harlow (Bundy Art Gallery), 1961-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Casa la Rosa - Chamberlain, Betty, 1956-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Casa la Rosa
      Catholic Student Center of Minnesota
      Cauduro, Ed
      CBS News
      Chakin, Nathan
      Chamberlain, Betty ( see also: Art Information Service)
    - Charity Exhibitions, 1960-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Chase Manhattan Bank - Cleveland Institute of Art, 1952-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Chase Manhattan Bank
      Chemists' Club
      Ching, William
      Chrysler, Walter P., Jr.
      Cimaise
      Cinema 16
      Citron, Kasper H.
      City Art Museum of St. Louis
      City of New York
      Clague, John
      Clare College
      Clark, Harold T.
      Clayburgh, A. M.
      Clert, Iris
      Cleveland Clinic Foundation
      Cleveland Convention and Visitors Bureau, Inc.
      Cleveland Council on World Affairs
      Cleveland Institute of Art
    - Cleveland Museum of Art, 1943-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
    - Cleveland Museum of Natural History - Cummings, Willard, 1954-1964; 1980-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Cleveland Museum of Natural History
      Cleveland News
      Cleveland Paint Varnish and Lacquer Association
      Cleveland Press
      Coe, Ralph M.
      Cohen, Barbara Joseloff
      Cohen, Bess J.
      Cohen, Ira
      Cohen, John H.
      Cohen, Joseph H.
      Cole, Timothy
      Collegiate School
      Colorado Springs Fine Arts Center
      Columbia Museum of Art
      Comité des arts du congrés pur la liberté de la culture
      Conde, John P.
      Container Corporation of America
      Contemporaries Gallery
      Contemporary Furniture Showrooms, Inc.
      Continental Bank
      Cook, Mrs. John
      Cooper, Mr.
      Cooper, Mrs. Henry C.
      Corcoran, Arthur
      Cordier and Ekstrom, Inc.
      CORE
      Cornell University
      Corporate Publications, Inc.
      Corrigan, Robert
      Council for the Retarded Child
      Cowan, Robert D.
      Cowie Galleries
      Cowles, John, Jr.
      Archibald Cox
      Cramer, Red and Beth
      Cramer, Worth C.
      Cranbrook Academy of Art
      Credit Bureau of Greater New York, Inc.
      Crehan, Hubert
      Crespi, H.
      Cross, Christopher
      Crown, Peter
      Crown Publishers, Inc.
      Cummings, Willard
    - Danes, Gibson A. - Dorfman, Ralph, 1957-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Danes, Gibson A.
      D'Arcy Advertising Agency
      D'Arcy Galleries
      Davenport, Leroy
      David Anderson Gallery (see: Anderson Gallery, David)
      Davidson, Barbara
      Davis, Abram D.
      Day, Lucien
      Day Nursery Association of Cleveland
      deAenllie Gallery, Roland
      Deitsch, Peter H.
      Delgado Museum of Fine Arts
      Dempsey, Jeanette
      Denny, Joann
      De Sauzé, Emile B.
      Des Moines Art Center
      Design Research
      Detroit Institute of Arts
      Dewey, Joseph
      Diamond, Harold
      Dickens,Charles
      Dietz, David
      Dilexi Gallery
      Dill, Bayard
      Dorfman, Ralph
    - Dotrement, Philippe, 1963-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Douglass College - Feigen, Richard L., 1977; 1957-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Douglass College
      Dowling, Robert W.
      Downey, Morton
      Downtown Gallery
      Duncan, Alexander D.
      Duschnes, Philip G.
      Dykes, Victor
      Eason, Winston
      Eden, Paul L.
      Editions de la Connaissance
      ?ditions M. Lacouriere
      Edmunds Scientific Co.
      Educational Alliance
      Efron, George
      Eiseman, Helen
      Eiseman, Philip
      Eliot, Elizabeth
      Elliott, Stanley B.
      Emerman, Bernard
      Emerson Public Schools
      England, Dan
      Ernest Wittenberg Public Relations (see: Wittenberg, Ernest, Public Relations)
      ESSO Research and Engineering Company
      Esther Robles Gallery (see: Robles Gallery, Esther)
      Evansville Museum of Arts and Science
      Eyles, Sybil
      Facchetti, Paul
      Fahnestock, Samuel L.
      Fairleigh Dickinson University
      Fairweather-Hardin Gallery
      FAR Gallery
      Feigen, Richard L.
    - Fenton Co., Inc., A. W., 1957-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Ferus Gallery - Garfinkel, Stanley, 1957-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Ferus Gallery
      Fike, C. A.
      Finch College Museum
      Fine Arts Associates
      Fine, Jacob
      FIT Alumni Association (see: Charity Exhibitions)
      Fitch, George H.
      Flannigan, Dennis
      Flesheim, S. W.
      Flint Institute of Arts
      Foshee, Rufus
      Four Seasons
      Fox, Claire
      Freeman, Stanley
      French, Winsor
      Fried Gallery, Rose
      Friedman, Frances R.
      Frumkin, Allen
      Fuldheim, Dorothy
      Gabriel, Robert
      Galerie Arnaud
      Galerie Claude Bernard
      Galerie d'Art Moderne
      Galerie D. Benador
      Galerie de France
      Galerie im Griechenbeisl
      Galerie Springer Berlin
      Galerie Stadler
      Galleria Nazionale d'Arte Moderna
      Gallery Conquistador
      Gallery Moos
      Gallery One
      Gallery Passport, Ltd.
      Gandola, Paul
      Gans, David M.
      Garfinkel, Stanley
    - Gauguin (carved cabinet), 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Geigy Chemical Corporation - Gimpel Fils, Ltd., 1957-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Geigy Chemical Corporation
      Geller, Abraham W.
      General Fireproofing Company
      Gerlach, Rose D.
      Gerson, Otto, Gallery
      Gibbs, David
      Gifford, Sanford
      Gilford Leather Co.
      Gimpel Fils, Ltd.
    - Gingrich, Arnold - Gutman, Walter, 1978; 1957-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Gingrich, Arnold
      Glickman, Charles
      Goeritz, Mathias
      Golodowsky, Noah
      Gonzales, Boyer
      Goodman, N. N.
      Goodman, Percival
      Goodman, Robert B.
      Goodrich Industrial Products
      Goodsell, C. H.
      Gotham Gallery
      Grace Borgenicht Gallery, Inc. (see: Borgenicht Gallery, Inc., Grace)
      Graff, Robert D.
      Graham Gallery
      Green, Mrs. Charles (Peggy)
      Green, Edward J.
      Greenstein, A. M.
      Gres Gallery
      Gries, Robert Hays
      Griesinger, Frank
      Gropius, Walter
      Grossman, Ethel
      Grossman, Marc J.
      Grove Press
      Grund, David
      Gruzen, B. Sumner
      Guggenheim Foundation
      Guillermin and Mollet
      Gump's
      Gutman, Walter
    - Haas, Albert - Hurd, K. F., 1950-1966; 1976; 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Haas, Albert
      Hagen, Yvonne
      Hahn Bros. Fireproof Warehouses, Inc.
      Hall, John H.
      Halle Brothers
      Halle, Hortense
      Halle, Kay
      Halley, Donald M.
      Hallmark Art Awards
      Hammarstrum, Marianne
      Hamon, Jake L. and Nancy B.
      Hancy, Lawrence
      Hannibal, J.
      Harper's Bazaar
      Harris, Alfred W,
      Harrison and Abramowit
      Haskins, Lester
      Hathaway Brown School
      Haupt, Ira
      Hawken School
      Hawkins, Erick
      Hayward, Elizabeth
      Hayter, S.W.
      Hazen, Joseph H.
      Hecht, Sidney A.
      Heller, Ben
      Hempel, Gardiner
      Henderson, Priscilla A. B.
      Herbert, David
      Herron Art Institute, John
      Hilda Carmel Gallery (see: Carmel Gallery, Hilda)
      Hillman, Kay Merrill
      Hiser, Mrs. Harold R., Jr.
      H. N. Abrams, Incorporated (see: Abrams Incorporated, H. N.)
      Hoffman, Junius
      Hollis, H. C.
      Holzheimers' Interiors
      Hooker, Mrs. R. W.
      Hoover Company
      Horan, Frank J.
      Horung, Robert
      Horton, John
      House and Garden
      Howard, Alice
      Hrabick, William J.
      Hurd, K. F.
    - IBM Proposal - Joslyn Art Museum, 1957-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
      IBM Proposal
      Igell, Herman
      Illinois Wesleyan University
      Institute of Contemporary Arts, London
      International Directory of Arts
      Iolas Gallery, Alexander
      Irwin, Spencer D.
      Isaacs Gallery
      Isaacs, Reginald R.
      Isserman, Ferdinand M.
      It Is
      Jackson Gallery, Martha
      James Bourlet and Sons, Ltd. (see: Bourlet and Sons, Ltd., James)
      James Gallery
      James, Wanda
      Janis, Sidney, Gallery
      Janss, Edwin
      Jayfro
      Jerrold Morris International Gallery Limited (see: Morris International Gallery Limited, Jerrold)
      John and Mabel Ringling Museum of Art (see: Ringling Museum of Art, John and Mabel)
      John Herron Art Institute (see: Herron Art Institute, John)
      Johns-Manvillle
      Johnson, Margarita
      Johnson, Philip C.
      Johnson, Theodate
      Joseph, Frank E.
      Joslyn Art Museum
    - Kane, Michael - KYW Television, 1973; 1957-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Kane, Michael
      Kareka, R. C.
      Katan, Maurits
      Kelleher, Joe
      Kelsey, Sam
      Kennedy, Jacqueline
      Kenneth Lynch and Sons (see: Lynch and Sons, Kenneth)
      Kent School
      Ketterer, Roman Norbert
      Kiefer, Anna A.
      Kinney, Anna
      Kirstein, Lincoln